<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>FA49 Proponent Office Blog on FA49 Proponent Office Blog</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in FA49 Proponent Office Blog on FA49 Proponent Office Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 FA49 Proponent Office</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Congratulations, you&#39;re an ORSA! Now What?</title>
      <link>/post/congratulations-you-re-an-orsa-now-what/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/congratulations-you-re-an-orsa-now-what/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Now that you&amp;rsquo;ve signed your letter stating your intent to transfer into FA49, it&amp;rsquo;s natural to wonder what you need to do now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;prepare-either-for-advanced-civil-schooling-or-the-orsa-military-applications-course-orsa-mac&#34;&gt;Prepare either for Advanced Civil Schooling or the ORSA Military Applications Course (ORSA-MAC)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wrote &lt;a href=&#34;/post/so-you-want-to-be-an-orsa/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a post&lt;/a&gt; detailing what to do if you need to refresh your fundamental math skills. The same advice applies. A couple of other considerations you need to know is that if you received acceptance for VTIP in the first quarter (Usually August - September), then you will have a short window to apply for ACS and gain acceptance to a civilian institution of study. The reason for this is that the VTIP results usually come out in early December and you will have very little time to meet the application deadlines for various graduate schools. The bottom line is plan early and keep this in mind when you apply for VTIP during the first quarter of the fiscal year, especially when scheduling your GRE.  If you apply during the third quarter board (usually February - March), then you have time to get your academic and other requirements in order before the next ACS panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;join-our-milbook-group&#34;&gt;Join our milBook group&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.milsuite.mil/book/groups/fa49-orsa&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;milBook&lt;/a&gt; group is our primary method of communicating with the current ORSA community. Once you join the group, just follow us through connection streams, emails, and inbox watches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;learn-about-your-potential-first-assignment-on-our-assignments-wiki&#34;&gt;Learn about your potential first assignment on our assignments wiki&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We just developed &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.milsuite.mil/wiki/FA49_Assignments_Info&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a wiki page&lt;/a&gt; that allows ORSAs to add any pertinent detail about their current assignment to help others with their assignment considerations and PCS preparations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just a couple things to think about. The majority of the questions you will have about your first assignment will be handled through the assignment officer, but the propoenent office is also available to help and advice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So you want to be an ORSA?</title>
      <link>/post/so-you-want-to-be-an-orsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/so-you-want-to-be-an-orsa/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;For this post, we will assume you have read the current version of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.milsuite.mil/book/groups/smartbook-da-pam-600-3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;DA PAM 600-3&lt;/a&gt;, any current information about &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hrc.army.mil/content/Officers%20Voluntary%20Transfer%20Incentive%20Program%20VTIP&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;VTIP&lt;/a&gt;, our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.milsuite.mil/book/docs/DOC-386817&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;FA49 Proponent Update&lt;/a&gt;, and our &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.milsuite.mil/book/docs/DOC-327917&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Data Science Vision&lt;/a&gt;.  If you haven&amp;rsquo;t, then please read these documents to get a sense of FA49 as a functional area, and what skills we are seeking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-exactly-are-we-looking-for&#34;&gt;What exactly are we looking for?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are evaluating three things for VTIP candidates:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your manner of performance in your current branch;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your potential for learning and applying profound mathematical thinking;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your operational experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;manner-of-performance&#34;&gt;Manner of performance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afer reading DA PAM 600-3, it should be clear that FA49 as a functional area does not have any key developed (KD) jobs for captains. Therefore, you will need to get an honest assessment for your promotion potential at your current grade since we will do a similar evaluation of your record. You can, of course, get this done with your assignment officer or any trusted mentor that will give you honest feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;profound-mathematical-thinking&#34;&gt;Profound mathematical thinking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read this far and have an interest in FA49, then it&amp;rsquo;s no secret that ORSAs need to know some mathematics. In particular, the math we apply is based on calculus, probability, and statistics. To learn more about how we use these types of mathematics click on the &amp;ldquo;what we do&amp;rdquo;link at the top of the page.  While the mathematics we study is not unique, it is how we apply math in our job that makes ORSAs a value-added member of the staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/How-Not-Be-Wrong-Mathematical/dp/0143127535/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1510624732&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=jordan+ellenberg+how+not+to+be+wrong&amp;amp;dpID=51Fi8hXVptL&amp;amp;preST=_SY291_BO1,204,203,200_QL40_&amp;amp;dpSrc=srch&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jordan Ellenberg&lt;/a&gt;, in his book &amp;ldquo;How Not to Be Wrong: The Power of Mathematical Thinking,&amp;rdquo; described profound mathematical thinking best when he says&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mathematical ideas we want to address are ones that can be engaged directly and profitably, whether your mathematical training stops at pre-algebra or extends much further. And they are not &amp;ldquo;mere facts,&amp;rdquo; like a simple statement of arithmetic&amp;ndash;they are principles, whose application extends far beyond the things you&amp;rsquo;re used to thinking of as mathematical. They are the go-to tools on the utility belt, and used properly they will help you not be wrong (2014 p. 16).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, what we are looking for here is your aptitude to learn profound mathematical thinking. This ultimately means we will need to evaluate your undergraduate or graduate level coursework. When doing so, we are looking for the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Officers must have completed at least one semester of calculus. FA49 foundational schools require three semesters of calculus (up through Multi-variable Calc) as a pre-requisite for entry into the Operations Research master’s program;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Officers must have an undergraduate degree in Science, Technology, Engineering, or Mathematics (STEM);&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If officers do not possess one of the required undergraduate degrees, they must have either GRE results within the past five years with a quantitative score higher than 153 in the new scoring system or show competency in calculus and statistics with a 3.0 GPA or greater in those classes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;operational-experience&#34;&gt;Operational Experience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The takeaway for you is that we do not reject anyone based on their basic branch. In fact, we are seeking to have a balance of as many basic branches within our functional area, because your operational experience brings a way of thinking and knowledge base that we can&amp;rsquo;t readily access as each cohort year group progresses through the ranks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-to-do-if-you-don-t-meet-our-technical-requirements&#34;&gt;What to do if you don&amp;rsquo;t meet our technical requirements?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best advice we can give is for you to complete calculus I-III as quickly as possible and an applied statistics course. Completing these courses will accomplish two things for you. First, you will have an easier time of obtaining a yes vote on your academic evaluation for VTIP. Second, you will have the required mathematical foundation courses for enrollment in ACS or our ORSA Military Applications Course (ORSA-MAC). As mentioned earlier, you can submit a GRE as long as your quantitative score is above 153. Your GRE score will primarily help us to determine your chances of being accepted into a graduate-level program, but we can&amp;rsquo;t emphasize enough the importance of making sure you have a solid grasp of calculus and statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two schools that work with the military and have the requisite courses are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amu.apus.edu/academic/schools/science-technology-engineering-and-math/bachelors/mathematics.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;American Military University&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.umuc.edu/academic-programs/course-information.cfm?course=MATH&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;University of Maryland University College&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-to-do-if-you-are-qualified-but-your-branch-is-currently-closed-for-vtip&#34;&gt;What to do if you are qualified but your branch is currently closed for VTIP?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The options you have available to you are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Submit an exception to policy along with your VTIP packet. Keep in mind your current branch will have a reason on why your year group is closed, and your branch will have quite a bit of influence with regards to final approval.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If your year group has passed the VTIP consideration cycle, then you can submit a branch transfer at any time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Science</title>
      <link>/project/data-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/data-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As you view the metro-like map of the skills needed for data science, you will quickly notice that this relatively new discipline utilizes just about every tool within an ORSAs toolkit. The goal of the data scientist is the same as any other analyst; helping leaders make better decisions. The challenge, however, of getting the critical pieces of information to support the decision is entirely different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get an idea of the type of challenge facing a data scientist, let&amp;rsquo;s think a little bit about the kinds of problems they are working on for the military. ORSAs within cyber organizations have to deal with cyber-related alerts to the Army network. Imagine all the antivirus, phishing attacks, and other warnings that occur from the millions of laptops, desktops, mobile devices across the Army&amp;rsquo;s network. Without going into the details, just extracting a small sample of that information is not a trivial task, and then to organize the data into a meaningful way to do analysis is another challenge onto itself. These types of tasks focus on approaches to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/blog/let-data-scientists-be-data-mungers&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;munge&lt;/a&gt; or transform data from its raw unstructured form into something structured for analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another challenge facing data scientists involves using various methods of artificial intelligence, such as machine learning, to train computers to do tasks that can augment humans. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@ageitgey/machine-learning-is-fun-part-3-deep-learning-and-convolutional-neural-networks-f40359318721&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;image classification&lt;/a&gt; is one of the first applications of machine learning. You can imagine how we could leverage the same types of algorithms to assist imagery analysts in identifying an enemy and friendly systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two small examples are just a tiny fraction of the myriad of applications for data science. Just like the other techniques of operations research, data scientists will help solve issues spanning across every aspect of the Army enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimization</title>
      <link>/project/optimization/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/optimization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When you optimize, the goal is to find the minimum or maximum quantities of a given objective function, subject to specified constraints. For the military, optimization has practical applications for multiple areas including force structure, cost analysis, human resources analysis, equipping, force rotations, logistics planning, infrastructure resilience, military intelligence, and many others. A graduate level program involving optimization usually focuses on three techniques: &lt;a href=&#34;https://brilliant.org/wiki/linear-programming/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;linear programming&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Integer_programming&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;integer programming&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nonlinear_programming&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;nonlinear programming&lt;/a&gt;. From there, you may also learn about one of the most versatile applications of optimization; &lt;a href=&#34;http://neddimitrov.org/teaching/networks-lecture-videos.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;network flows and graphs&lt;/a&gt;, and other optimization techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simulations</title>
      <link>/project/simulations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/simulations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Learning about simulations is one of the first subjects in which an ORSA moves from theory into application. A simulation is merely a representation of a real-world system or process over time. There are several reasons why you would use a simulation, but a key reason to use simulations is that a reasonable calculation or statistical analysis could not happen otherwise.  In other words, the system we are analyzing is too complicated to narrow its essence into a series of equations. For military ORSAs, our involvement with simulations usually focuses on some variant of a combat model. Since combat between two forces involves multiple factors, there is not a single simulation capable of replicating this type of complexity. Thus, analyses involving simulations incorporate experts from numerous disciplines such as applied mathematicians, computer scientists, physicists, ORSAs, and other military experts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Inference</title>
      <link>/project/statistical-inference/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/statistical-inference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With probability, ORSAs learn how to develop models and make predictions of the relative likelihood of individual events happening within these models. Statistics, on the other hand, takes a given sample of data and tries to predict the model that produced the data to make inferences about general population the sample represents. Kalid Azad, the creator of the Better Explained blog, has a great &lt;a href=&#34;https://betterexplained.com/articles/a-brief-introduction-to-probability-statistics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; that provides an excellent analogy describing the relationship between probability and statistics. In short, probability is taking measurements of an animal, and deduce what kind of tracks they would leave. Conversely, a statistician will find a footprint and determine which type of animal produced it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For ORSAs, statistics is our Swiss Army Knife. We will collect descriptive statistics of the data to find out parameters such as the mean, standard deviation, and other items to get a sense of the structure of the data and the types of data we can use for further analysis. From there we will explore the data visually and otherwise, and depending on the problem, conduct more prescriptive statistics to develop analytics. In other words, we look through data and glean out the most critical aspects of that data to give insights that were not obvious before the analysis. The tutorials and publications in this section will provide some examples of how we do that. In addition to the mathematics listed in the &lt;a href=&#34;/project/probability-modeling/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;probability modeling&lt;/a&gt; section, you will also need to learn &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.khanacademy.org/math/linear-algebra&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;linear algebra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Secretary Problem</title>
      <link>/tutorial/secretary-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tutorial/secretary-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Being an ORSA is not unlike any other job on the command staff. That is, you will get a question to answer, and depending on your experience level and the complexity of the issue, you can sometimes give a quick response, or you may need more time to provide a thorough answer and explanation. The problem that follows in this white paper is an example of the type of problem an ORSA would deal with in their line of work. In particular, this question deals with determining the probability of an event, given specific pieces of information. The approach used to solve this problem is a method based on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://datagenetics.com/blog/december32012/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;secretary problem&lt;/a&gt;. The example that follows is an excellent problem to show not only an application of probability theory but how to solve a problem from multiple approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this problem, the ORSA can derive the solution with a couple of formulas.  While it is quick just to look up a formula and give an answer, it is crucial for ORSAs to understand how to gain an intuition for the mathematics they are using, so that they can translate their intuition into an appropriate analogy for the person who is receiving the final results. To put it another way, an ORSA needs to develop an ability to translate the findings of their analysis into a lexicon understood by the consumers of the report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;motivation&#34;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US Physical Fitness Center and School (USAPFCS) is researching to select a new Army Physical Fitness Uniform. Based on their request for proposal, the USAPFCS received 50 different uniform designs that meet the requirement, and they will need to choose
the best prototype before moving to the next phase of the acquisition process. Before deciding on the material solution to develop, the Program Manager for the uniform selection team wants to know the probability of selecting the best submission out of the 50 received since they are working with a limited budget and can only proceed with one material solution to develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;analysis&#34;&gt;Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some initial research, the procurement team ORSA determined the best model to use is one based on the secretary problem. That is the procurement team should:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review an initial set of &amp;lsquo;$k$&amp;rsquo; proposals out of the $n=50$ total proposals without making a selection. To ensure a fair assessment is given to each proposal, they are shuffled into a random order before the initial evaluation;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review the remaining $n-k$ proposals and choose the first proposal that is better than the
previous set of proposals;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If they make it to the last proposal, then by default this will be the selected proposal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;analytical-solution&#34;&gt;Analytical Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two simple formulas to find the optimal selection probability. First, the number of initial candidates to review is approximately equal to $n/e$. In other words, if you take the total number of proposals and divide it by the special constant $e$, then you will get a reasonable initial sample in which to review the remaining proposals. In this example, the initial number of candidates to review is $\left\lfloor50/e\right\rfloor = 18$.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to find the probability of selecting the best candidate, all that is left is to use the formula $$-\left(\frac{k}{n}\right)\ln\left(\frac{k}{n}\right)$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this formula produces the following solution:
$$
\begin{aligned}
\text{selection probability} &amp;amp; = -\left(\frac{k}{n}\right)\ln\left(\frac{k}{n}\right) \\&lt;br /&gt;
\phantom{\vspace} \\&lt;br /&gt;
\text{selection probability} &amp;amp; = -\left(\frac{18}{50}\right)\ln\left(\frac{18}{50}\right) \\&lt;br /&gt;
\phantom{\vspace} \\&lt;br /&gt;
\text{selection probability} &amp;amp; = 0.3677944
\end{aligned}
$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before going back to the procurement team with the answer, the ORSA needs to make sure they can answer the question of why this is the correct answer. One way to do this is to create a plot showing the relationship between the number of initial candidates to evaluate $k$ and the probability of optimal selection. &lt;a href=&#34;#figure1&#34;&gt;Figure 1&lt;/a&gt; below shows this link, and the red dot indicates the maximum probability. Primarily, as the number of proposals in your initial rejection region increases, the chance of selecting the ideal candidate increases as well until you reached a maximum at 18 proposals. After 18 proposals, the probability of choosing the best proposal decreases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;figure1&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/img/secplot.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Plot showing the optimal selection probability versus the number of initial candidates reviewed.&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result should make sense because, before 18 proposals, we don&amp;rsquo;t have enough information to determine which bid is indeed the best one. Along the same lines, after 18 proposals, we reviewed more proposals than necessary to decide on the optimal probability. Feeling satisfied with this logic, the ORSA would then present their findings to the procurement team, and life is good. However, there are some occasions when just giving this amount of information is not enough. For example, a procurement team member may want to know more about why 18 is the appropriate number. While they can see the graphic that shows this, their intuition is not sufficient to grasp the presented formulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the ORSA could deal with this in various ways. One approach would involve deriving the formula, similar to the process shown by  &lt;a href=&#34;http://datagenetics.com/blog/december32012/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Data Genetics&lt;/a&gt;. I would not recommend this method unless you are convening with a bunch of people that have an overwhelming enjoyment of math. To put it another way, most of the consumers of our analysis don&amp;rsquo;t share that type of enthusiasm as we do. Therefore, you will need to find a way to report just enough information to build trust with the results without delving into the abstract details on a subject that your message gets lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;simulate-the-process-to-develop-intuition&#34;&gt;Simulate the process to develop intuition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A better approach would involve creating a less complicated example and then gradually increase the complexity in a way that is more intuitive. A simulation, of the selection process, for instance, could guide the intuition of why the formula works. Because the simulation closely resembles the selection process, it will be easier to see how the formula reduces to its final form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;a-minimal-example&#34;&gt;A minimal example&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand, how the simulation works, let&amp;rsquo;s examine a simple example. The table below shows the results of reviewing three proposals with a strategy to evaluate and reject the first proposal and select the next proposal that scores higher than the first one. The rows indicate the final rating for each proposal, with a score of one for the worst proposal and three for the best proposal. The boldface numbers are the selected proposals by the selection strategy, and the red highlighted selections were instances of choosing the highest rated proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, the simulation will create a random sample of scores that has a sample size equal to the total number of bids to evaluate. This example shows three, while the simulation we will use has a sample size of 50. After we create a random, sample, the simulation will enforce the rules of rejecting the initial number of candidates and then selecting the first proposal better than the previously seen proposals. If the simulation reaches the last proposal, then that proposal is chosen by default. After collecting all the winning bids, the simulation will compute the probability of selecting the best candidate by dividing the total number of times the highest proposal was selected divided by the total number of trials simulated. As indicated by the table, this simulation produced an optimal selection probability of $50\%$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;caption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table 1:&lt;/strong&gt; Example simulation results&lt;/caption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;simulation-results&#34;&gt;Simulation results&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#figure2&#34;&gt;Figure 2&lt;/a&gt; displays the results of simulating the selection of candidate proposals, with an initial review sample ranging from 1 to 49 samples, for 100, 1,000, and 100,000 trials respectively. The figure also contains a plot of the analytical solution shown in &lt;a href=&#34;#figure1&#34;&gt;Figure 1&lt;/a&gt;.  Thus, what the figure shows that as the number of trials increase, the simulation results will start to closely mimic the results of the analytic solution. To put this another way, the analytical formula is what the simulation would return with an infinite number of trials. Table 2 shows a summary of this described pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;figure2&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;/img/simulation-results.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Simulation results for 100 trials.&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Number of trials&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Number of inital candidates to review&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Optimal probability&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12, 15, 21, 29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.400&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.383&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100,000&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.375&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$\infty$&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.368&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;caption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table 2:&lt;/strong&gt; Comparison of simulation results&lt;/caption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This white paper demonstrated how to apply a probability model towards selecting the best proposal from a pool of 50 proposals. Using a simple formula solved the problem, but we also learned that besides solving the problem, an ORSA must have a good intuitive sense of what the formula is doing. For an ORSA, that would usually involve diving into the background theory of the formula, but doing that process for a non-technical audience is usually not the best approach. A better approach would be to use a simple simulation, or similar technique, that would show what is happening underneath the hood of the formula. Ultimately, this helps to build trust with the ORSA&amp;rsquo;s analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;futher-learning&#34;&gt;Futher learning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about the secretary problem in general, then read &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.math.upenn.edu/~ted/210F10/References/Secretary.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Thomas Ferguson&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; paper on the history of this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The YouTube video below presents Dr. Ria Symonds and her application of the secretary problem to selecting the best port-o-potty during a music festival.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/ZWib5olGbQ0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34; title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;The $\left\lfloor \right\rfloor$ symbol represents the floor function, and it means to take the result of the evaluated expression and round to the nearest integer that is less than or equal to the usual result of the evaluated expression. The mathematical constant, $e$, is also referred to as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mathsisfun.com/numbers/e-eulers-number.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Euler&amp;rsquo;s number&lt;/a&gt;. 
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Probability Modeling</title>
      <link>/project/probability-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/probability-modeling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this section, you can find out what ORSAs learn about probability theory and how we apply that approach towards using probability models in some of our analyses. Most operations research programs start out with a course on probability theory. The image in the header, for example, shows the equation for Baye&amp;rsquo;s theorem, a Markov chain, a decision tree, and a Venn diagram. These are just a small sample of the myriad of probability models available to an ORSA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although colleges teach probability and statistics as one course at the undergraduate level, there is a clear distinction between these two disciplines that an ORSA must understand. For an excellent short explanation of these differences, see this article from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www3.cs.stonybrook.edu/~skiena/jaialai/excerpts/node12.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Stony Brook University&lt;/a&gt;. To gain an intuition for probability theory, you will need to have a good foundation in the mathematics of &lt;a href=&#34;https://artofproblemsolving.com/videos/counting&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;counting&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLDDGPdw7e6Ag1EIznZ-m-qXu4XX3A0cIz&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;discrete mathematics&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.khanacademy.org/math/calculus-home?t=classes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;calculus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Organizing Your Data Closet</title>
      <link>/publication/latent-class-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/latent-class-analysis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
